Okay, so in this video then, let's talk
about EAC.
Now EAC is estimate at completion.
An estimate at completion is your
forecasted budget.
Now, there are four formulas that you need
to know for EAC, right?
And these are the four different formulas.
Now, why are they four formulas?
Well, in reality, there's actually many,
many more.
There's many, many more formulas for EAC.
But these are just the four that you need
for the PMP exam.
Now, what is EAC?
right.
Forecasted budget.
The BAC budget at completion, that is our
original budget.
That's our original baseline budget.
Now, are we always going to meet that
original budget?
Maybe, maybe not.
So what's our forecasted budget then?
If we've overspent or
underspent so far, then what's
our projection now for
the end of the project?
That is our forecasted budget.
And so there's, And the reason why there's
different ways of calculating that is
because there's different assumptions that
you could be making.
What's our rate of performance,
right, for the rest of the project?
We're at a certain point in the project,
right, so in this scenario that we've been
using, we are halfway through the project,
we are 50% of the way through the project,
well, we still have the
other 50% of the project to go
through, right, or the
other 50% of the project left.
Well, what's our, what's our expectation
or what's our assumption for how we're
going to perform for the rest of the
project?
Are we going to work at the same rate?
Are we going to work at a different rate?
Are we going to improve our performance?
It takes all of that into consideration.
And that's why there's four different
formulas here.
Now, I'm going to go through each of these
formulas, right?
But really, it's these middle two that
usually come up more on the exam.
These are the ones that are more popular
ones.
So I'm going to talk about one and four
just to get them out of the way and then
the next slide we will do some
calculations on these middle two.
Now you need to know these formulas,
you also need to know when to use them.
So in the exam, if they say, if they give
you a bunch of numbers and they'll say,
calculate EAC, well there's four different
EAC formulas, which one do we use?
Right.
So you need to know when to use them,
right?
All right, so you would use the first one,
The first one is AC plus bottom up ETC.
It could also say new ETC, right,
but generally bottom-up ETC.
You're going to use this if
somewhere in the question it says
a new estimate is required, a
new cost estimate is required.
Original estimates were wrong,
right?
Or the original estimates were too high
level.
Remember, bottom-up means a very detailed
estimate, right?
So that's when he'd use this first one,
right?
For somewhere in the question it says the
original estimate is required.
You do this fourth one, right?
If it says, somewhere in the question,
it says, poor cost performance,
you have to hit firm completion date,
Right, and then spend the schedule is
going to impact the cost, I know,
that kind of thing.
So that's when you
use this formula, AC plus
B, A, C, minus E, V,
divided by CPI times SPI.
Right, your schedule performance is going
to impact your cost performance.
Right, so that's when you'd use this
fourth one.
Again, number one and number four,
not as likely to come up.
Not that it won't come up, but it's not as
common.
By far, it's number two and three.
So let's go through the calculations on
these.
on those two.
Now, remember our scenario here then,
right?
We're five weeks into the 10-week project,
costing $100,000 and $40% complete,
and we've spent $60,000 so far.
Now, the second EAC formula then,
which is AC plus BAC minus EV, right?
You're going to use this if
somewhere in the question, it
says future spending will
be at the budgeted rate, right?
They'll mention something about budgeted
rate.
Either spending continues at the budgeted
rate, right, or work continues at the
budgeted rate, or it
could say variances are
atypical, variances are
not going to continue, right?
Then you'd use this second EAC formula.
Now, BAC remember, is the original budget,
original baseline budget.
The original baseline budget for our
project is $100,000.
All right, so these are the metrics that
we have so far, right?
from, you know, previous calculations on
previous videos, right?
We've got our actual cost of $60,000,
right?
So we've got our budget given to us.
In fact, the actual cost is also given to
us in the question.
The original budget given to us $100,000
and the earned value $40,000.
That's what we've done so far.
So plug the numbers in, and we get
$120,000.
Now, let's talk about this.
What does this mean?
Future spending will be
at the budgeted rate, or
variances will, what are
atypical, will not continue.
What this is saying is that whatever
variances we have experienced, that's it.
We're not going to go any further over
budget or any further behind schedule.
In this case, we're talking about the
budget.
So however much over budget we have gone
or under budget, you know, that's it.
It will just remain.
So whatever the reason
was for these variances,
the atypical, they will not continue.
So my road example, We
went, you know, our cost
variance we calculated was
$20,000 or negative $20,000.
So in other words, we've gone $20,000 over
budget so far, right?
And the assumption is that we will just
remain $20,000 over budget.
We're not going to go any further over
budget.
And if that's the case,
our original budget is
$100,000, our project
will finish up at $120,000.
Right.
So that is using this assumption,
right?
And it's to say it's going to work every
time, right?
That calculation is going to work every
time.
Right.
So what I had just said, right,
you could, you know, plug the numbers in.
It's basically saying that,
you know, future spending will
be at the budgeted rate or
variances will not continue.
However over budget or under budget we've
gone, that's it.
That will just remain.
Now, what if we decide that, you know
what, we've been working really
inefficiently so far,
or inefficiently, and we
will just continue working
at the exact same rate.
So, in other words, spending will continue
at the current rate, or current cost
performance index will continue,
we'll be working at the same rate.
Variances are typical, variances will
continue.
Then we use this formula, BAC divided by
CPS.
right because we're going to be working at
the same rate and this case you know the
the ESE is always talking about in terms
of the cost right so whatever cost we've
been increasing right we've been working
really inefficiently so far we'll just
continue working at the same inefficient
rate right all we've been working
efficiently so far we'll continue working
at the same efficient rate so in our
example right of building this road we've
been working inefficiently our CPI that we
calculated in previous video is only 0.67,
right?
So our BSE original
budget, right, budget at
completion 100,000, divided
by 0.67, we get 150,000.
So in other words, if we continue working
at the same rate that we've been working
at so far, our project will finish up at
150,000.
If we can go back to the budgeted rate,
right, if what we've experienced so far,
we've gone over budget, $20,000,
if we don't go any further over budget,
our project will finish up at 120.
But if we continue working at the same
rate, our project will finish about 150,
$150,000.
So that's the basic difference between
these two ESE formulas.